Guide to the Konstanty Jeleński Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Papers Relating to Witold Gombrowicz, 1951-1987; Series II; 2.92; (7 boxes)
  - Writings
    - Writings of Others on Gombrowicz
      - [Clauvel, Jacques?], essay on Gombrowicz, manuscript, undated (Box 8, Folder 225)
      - Fryde, Ludwik, "O Ferdydurke Gombrowicza," typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 8, Folder 226)
      - [Georgin, Rosine], "Paléontologie de Witold Gombrowicz," typescript (copy), corrected, undated (Box 9, Folder 227-228)
      - Grad, Steve, essay on Gombrowicz, typescript (copy), undated (Box 9, Folder 229)
        Includes a note from Jeleński to Dominique de Roux.
      - Gustafson, Lars, "A une grande première du Dramaten," typescript, undated (Box 9, Folder 230)
      - Hamilton, Alastair, essay on Gombrowicz and Vence, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 9, Folder 231)
      - Hartung, Rudolf, "Witold Gombrowicz, Indizien," typescript carbon, undated (Box 9, Folder 232)
      - Jomy, Alain and Bastid, Jean-Pierre, La Pornographie, typescript (copy), undated (Box 9, Folder 233)
      - Kamil, Maria, "Ulica bagatella...", typescript, corrected, undated (Box 9, Folder 234)
      - Katarasinski, Jerzy, "Comme dans une operette," French translation by Jeleński, holograph (and copy), 1975 (Box 9, Folder 235)
      - Kijowski, Andrzej, "Strategia Gombrowicza," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 9, Folder 236)
      - Kosinski, Jerzy; "Mortgaged to oneself: The Cosmos of Witold Gombrowicz," typescript (copy), 1970 (Box 9, Folder 237)
      - Kott, Jan, "O Slubie Gombrowicza," typescript, corrected (copy), undated (Box 9, Folder 238)
      - Malic, Zdravko
        - "Bibliographie de la critique polonaise sur Witold Gombrowicz," typescript, corrected, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 239)
        - " Slub Witolda Gombrowicza," typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 9, Folder 240)
        - " Trans-Atlantyk Witolda Gombrowicza," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 9, Folder 241)
      - Morawiec, Elżbieta, "Rytualy Gombrowicza," typescript carbon, corrected, 1980? (Box 9, Folder 242)
      - Mrożek, Sławomir
        - Essay on Gombrowicz, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 9, Folder 243)
        - "Gombrowicz. La mort," French translation by Jeleński, holograph, undated (Box 9, Folder 244)
      - Mrozowski, Henryk Janusz, La Pornographie, typescript (copy), undated (Box 9, Folder 245)
      - Oks, Mario, "Trayectoria de Gombrowicz en la Argentina," typescript, corrected (and copy), undated (Box 9, Folder 246)
      - Otwinowski, Stefan, "Gombrowicz w Warszawie," typescript, corrected and French translation by Jeleński ("Gombrowicz a Varsovie"), typescript, corrected, undated (Box 10, Folder 247)
      - Piñero, Virgilio, "Gombrowicz por el mismo," typescript, corrected, and copy, undated (Box 10, Folder 248)
      - Przyłuski, Bronisław, " Operetka Witolda Gombrowicza," typescript, corrected, 1967 (Box 10, Folder 249)
        Includes a letter from Przyłuski to Jeleński.
      - Salamon, Joanna, essays on Gombrowicz and SPrzyłuskiowacki, typescripts (copies), 1987 (Box 10, Folder 250)
        Includes letters from Salamon to Jeleński.
      - Sandauer, Artur
        - "Gombrowicz a Polska," typescript and copy, and French translation ("Gombrowicz et la Pologne), typescript carbon, undated (Box 10, Folder 251)
        - "Listy Witolda Gombrowicza," typescript carbon, undated (Box 10, Folder 252)
        - "Witold Gombrowicz, L'homme et l'ecrivain," French translation by Anna Posner, printed version, 1965 (Box 10, Folder 253)
      - Skorupski, Kazimierz, "Spor Wokół Trans-Atlantyku Witolda Gombrowicza," typescript (copy), 1977 (Box 10, Folder 254)
      - [Szubska, Barbara], "Gombrowicz et les Polonais," typescript, corrected by Gombrowicz, undated (Box 10, Folder 255)
      - Szymkowicz-Gombrowicz, Jerzy, "Komentarz biograficzny do twórczości Witolda Gombrowicza," typescript (copy), 1967 (Box 10, Folder 256)
      - Venard, Michele, "L'Histoire de Gombrowicz," typescript (copy), undated (Box 10, Folder 257)
      - Unidentified essay in Polish, typescript, undated (Box 10, Folder 258)
  - Other Papers
    - Contract between Wydawnictwo Likerackie and Institut littéraire regarding Gombrowicz's works, manuscript draft by Jeleński (carbon), typescript draft (copy), final contract, signed (copy), 1981 (Box 10, Folder 259)
    - Copies of documents relating to Gombrowicz (Box 10, Folder 260)
    - Printed material on Gombrowicz, circa 1964-1986 (Box 11, Folder 261-277)
    - Printed material on Gombrowicz, circa 1964-1986 (Box 12, Folder 278-286)
- Papers Relating to the Congress for Cultural Freedom, 1959-1976; Series III; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  Series III is organized into three subseries: Correspondence, Reports and Memoranda, and Printed Material.
  Series III documents Jelenski's involvement with the Congress for Cultural Freedom. Much of the material dates from the time surrounding a scandal in which ties between the Congress and the Central Intelligence Agency were publicized in 1967. The Congress subsequently changed its name to the International Association for Cultural Freedom. Correspondence is with other affiliates of the Congress and discusses various activities, focusing on Eastern European politics during the 1960s and 1970s. Reports and memoranda document the activities of the Congress in the areas of political activism, the arts, and research into pacifism and violence as methods of social change. Printed material consists of newspaper clippings about the Congress and about topics related to activities of the Congress.
  - Correspondence
    - Emmanuel, Pierre to Konstanty Jeleński, 1967 (Box 13, Folder 287)
    - Griffith, William E. to Michael Josselson (copy), 1965 September 30 (Box 13, Folder 288)
    - Hunt, John, 1959 (Box 13, Folder 289)
    - Jeleński, Konstanty to Pierre Emmanuel, 1967, undated (Box 13, Folder 290)
    - Łabedz, Leopold to Konstanty Jeleński, 1967, undated (Box 13, Folder 291)
    - Łabedz, Leopold to Shepard Stone (copy), 1970 (Box 13, Folder 292)
    - Monegal, Emir Rodriquez to Konstanty Jeleński, 1967 (Box 13, Folder 293)
    - Nabokov, Nicolas to Konstanty Jeleński, 1967 February 28 (Box 13, Folder 294)
    - Pavlovic, Miodrag to Konstanty Jeleński, undated (Box 13, Folder 295)
    - Stone, Shepard to Konstanty Jeleński, 1971 August 26 (Box 13, Folder 296)
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 13, Folder 297)
  - Reports and Memoranda
    Arranged chronologically. Undated material is filed at the end of the listing.
    - Report on a trip to Yugoslavia, March 10-17, by Jeleński, typescript, corrected, circa 1959 (Box 13, Folder 298)
    - "Comite d'ecrivains et d'editeurs pour une entr'aide europeenne," typescript, photocopy, 1965 July 18 (Box 13, Folder 299)
    - Report of the Executive Committee, 1965 October 8-9 (Box 13, Folder 300)
    - "Rapport du voyage en Allemagne entrepris avec le Dr. Hans Oprecht du 22 au 25 novembre 1965," typescript (copy) (Box 13, Folder 301)
    - "Some Projects of the Writers' and Publishers' Committee for European Cooperation," typescript carbon, corrected, 1966 February (Box 13, Folder 302)
    - "The Galerie Lambert and the Writers' and Publishers' Committee for European Cooperation," typescript carbon, corrected, 1966 February (Box 13, Folder 303)
    - "The Writers' and Publishers' Committee for European Cooperation," typescript carbon, 1966 February (Box 13, Folder 304)
    - "International Council meeting, Societe européenne de Culture, Budapest," typescript carbon, 1966 September (Box 13, Folder 305)
    - "Action du Congrès envers l'Europe et l'Est" (memo from Jeleński to Emmanuel), typescript carbon, 1966 December 8 (Box 13, Folder 306)
    - Goldstein, D.I., memo to Pierre Emmanuel on Asian and African activities (copy), 1967 June 1 (Box 13, Folder 307)
    - "Le Congres et les revues," typescript carbon, 1967 June 6 (Box 13, Folder 308)
    - "Projet de rapport presente aux membres de la commission de reorganisation du Congres", 1967 June 16 (Box 13, Folder 309)
    - "Rapport presente aux membres de la commission de reorganisation du Congres pour la liberte de la culture en vue de l'assemblee generale du 23.9.1967," by Pierre Emmanuel, typescript carbon, corrected and typescript, 1967 July 10-20 (Box 13, Folder 310)
    - "Rapport presente par la commission de reorganisation du Congres pour la liberte de la culture a l'assemblee generale du 16 septembre 1967," typescript (copy), 1967 September (Box 13, Folder 311)
    - Table of organization and memorandum to Pierre Emmanuel, [1967] (Box 13, Folder 312)
    - "The Congress for Cultural Freedom 1950-1967," typescript (copy) (Box 13, Folder 313)
    - "International Association for Cultural Freedom (Suggestions for a program)," typescript (copy), [1967] (Box 13, Folder 314)
    - Notes on [Reactionary element?], by Jeleński, holograph, [1967] (Box 13, Folder 315)
    - Notes on the Assemblée Générale, by Jeleński, holograph, [1967] (Box 13, Folder 316)
    - "Seminar on Violence," notes and correspondence, 1968 (Box 13, Folder 317)
    - "Pacifism and violence -- Their uses and limitations as instruments of reform," typescript (copy), 1969 February (Box 13, Folder 318)
    - "The student rebellion and the future of Western industrial society," typescript (copy), 1969 April (Box 13, Folder 319)
    - "Some background material for the Alghero seminar on the student rebellion and the future of Western industrialized societies", typescript (copy), 1969 April (Box 13, Folder 320)
    - "Sources of political conflict in developed societies," by Ralf Dahrendorf, typescript (and copy), 1969 May (Box 13, Folder 321)
    - "The two and the many, speculations on East-West policy," by François Duchêne, typescript (copy), 1969 May (Box 13, Folder 322)
    - "The Alpbach European Forum," typescript (copy), 1969 May (Box 13, Folder 323)
    - "Suggestions for the 1970 I.A.C.F. Conference," by Jeleński, typescript (copy), 1969 July 1 (Box 13, Folder 324)
    - "Notes on a proposal for an IACF seminar on workshop on The socialist idea ", 1970 May 25 (Box 13, Folder 325)
    - "Science and human purpose," by Erich Jantsch, typescript (copy), 1970 August 29 (Box 13, Folder 326)
    - "Note pour Pierre Emmanuel," typescript carbon, 1970 December (Box 13, Folder 327)
    - Unidentified essay beginning "The metamorphosis of the past two centuries...", circa 1970 (Box 13, Folder 328)
    - Memo on the role of the Congress in Europe, by Jeleński and Shepard Stone, 1971 January 29 (Box 13, Folder 329)
    - "Remarques sur la reorganisation et le futur de l'association internationale pour la liberte de la culture," by Pierre Emmanuel, typescript carbon, 1971 April 1 (Box 13, Folder 330)
    - "K.A. Jelenski's intervention at the IACF Board of Directors Meeting October 3, 1971," typescript carbon (Box 13, Folder 331)
    - "Quelques notes sur la reorganisation du Congres," by Jeleński, holograph, [1971] (Box 13, Folder 332)
    - "Entretien avec John Hunt," by Jeleński, typescript carbon, 1972 May 7 (Box 13, Folder 333)
    - "Projet de lettre aux membres de la Commission pour l'avenir de l'AILC (Bullock, Stone, Kwapong, Denhoff, Shils)," by Pierre Emmanuel, typescript (copy), 1972 (Box 13, Folder 334)
    - Transcript of a conference [in Venice?] featuring Lubis, Bell, Taylor, Williams, Kolakowski, Ryan, Gellner, Harris, Letwin, Kockelmans and others, 1976 (Box 13, Folder 335)
    - "The Latin American Institute of International Relations," typescript (copy), undated (Box 13, Folder 336)
    - "The seminar program of the Congress," typescript (copy) with notes by Jeleński, undated (Box 13, Folder 337)
    - "Notes pour article de F.B. dans Preuves ", undated (Box 13, Folder 338)
    - "Eastern Europe," typescript carbon, undated (Box 14, Folder 339)
    - "Some remarks on Jelenski's reflections," typescript carbon, undated (Box 14, Folder 340)
    - Unidentified fragments, undated (Box 14, Folder 341-342)
  - Printed Material
    - Clippings, pamphlets and copies of articles relating to the Congress for Cultural Freedom, 1961-1968, undated (Box 14, Folder 343-350)
- Papers Relating to the Royaumont Foundation, 1969-1973; Series IV; 0.42; (1 box)
  Series IV is organized into three subseries: Correspondence, Notes, Reports and Memoranda, and Printed Material.
  Series IV documents the activities of the Royaumont Foundation in the late 1960s and early 1970s, focusing on the relationships among science, art, and culture. Founded in 1964, the Royaumont Foundation is a private cultural foundation that promotes research in the humanities.
  - Correspondence
    - Shattuck, Roger to Jacob Bronowski and J.E. Slater, 1969 August 6 (Box 15, Folder 351)
  - Notes, Reports and Memoranda
    - Fondation Royaumont, International Programs, Activities Report, 1971 (Box 15, Folder 352)
    - Jeleński, Konstanty
      - "La Nature dans l'homme"; typescript (copy), undated (Box 15, Folder 353)
      - "Bio-Anthropologie et culture contemporaine," typescript (copy), undated (Box 15, Folder 354)
      - "Bio-Anthropology and contemporary culture," typescript, undated (Box 15, Folder 355)
      - "Vers un programme culturel et artistique de l'Institut Royaumont," typescript carbon (and copy), undated (Box 15, Folder 356)
      - Notes, undated (Box 15, Folder 357)
    - Piatellei-Palmarini, Massimo, "Biological roots of the human individual," printed, signed, with manuscript notes by Jeleński., 1973 (Box 15, Folder 358)
    - Papers related to "L'Homme et la Mort," manuscript, typescript and printed material, 1973 (Box 15, Folder 359)
    - Unidentified, 1971 (Box 15, Folder 360)
  - Printed Material
    - Clippings and other printed material relating to the Royaumont Foundation, 1970-1973, undated (Box 15, Folder 361-362)
- Papers Relating to the Institut national de l'audiovisuel, 1979-1984; Series V; 0.21; (1 box)
  Series V documents the activities of the Institut national de l'audiovisuel in the late 1970s and early 1980s, focusing on art and film. Founded in 1974, the Institut national de l'audiovisuel is an archival repository for French film and television recordings.
  - Notes on Regards entendus, 1979 (Box 16, Folder 363)
  - "Quelques remarques concernant le projet d'une serie La lecon de peinture ," typescript (copies), 1979 (Box 16, Folder 364)
  - Notes on artists and poets, typescript (copy), undated (Box 16, Folder 365-366)
  - "Leonardo Cremonini et Marc Le Bot, les parentheses du regard," by Jeleński, typescript (copy), undated (Box 16, Folder 367)
  - Review of Receding futures, by Richard Calvocoressi, typescript, signed (and copy), 1980 (Box 16, Folder 368)
  - Notes on cubism, typescript (copies), 1980 (Box 16, Folder 369)
  - Articles for Regards entendus, typescript (copies), 1981 (Box 16, Folder 370)
  - Notes, typescript (copies), undated (Box 16, Folder 371)
  - Letter: Jerome Prieur to Michel Leiris, 1982 July 24 (Box 16, Folder 372)
  - Clippings, 1980-1984 (Box 16, Folder 373)
- Oversize Material
  - Dönhoff, Marion Gräfin, outgoing (Series I), 1984 (Box 17, Folder 374)
  - Photograph of Pope John Paul II inscribed to Jeleński (Series I), 1980 (Box 17, Folder 375)
  - Drawings, possibly illustrations for articles (copies) (Series I), undated (Box 17, Folder 376)
  - General clippings and copies of articles (Series I), 1981-1984, undated (Box 17, Folder 377-378)
  - "Bruno Schultz et Ferdydurke," holograph (copy), with notes by Jeleński (Series II), undated (Box 17, Folder 379)
  - "Gombrowicz et les Polonais," holograph (copy), with typewritten note (Series II), undated (Box 17, Folder 380)
  - Printed material on Gombrowicz (Series II), circa 1964-1986 (Box 18, Folder 381-387)
  - Clippings, pamphlets and copies of articles relating to the Congress for Cultural Freedom (Series III), 1961-1968, undated (Box 18, Folder 388-389)
  - Clippings and other printed material relating to the Royaumont Foundation (Series IV), 1970-1973, undated (Box 18, Folder 390)
- Restricted Fragile Material
  Conditions Governing Access
  Box 19 contains Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 12 (Box 19, Folder 391)
  - Box 14 (Box 19, Folder 392)
  - Box 18 (Box 19, Folder 393)